mosquitoes are not just a nuisance but
the carriers of disease like zika Dengue
Fever DEET has been the go-to repellent
for decades now so what does research
say about it safety and Effectiveness
and are there better natural
alternatives I'll answer these questions
in this video and the next
[Music]
the most dangerous animal in the world
isn't the great white or the king cobra
or lions and tigers and bears in fact
only about 10 people dying shark attacks
every year
coming in number two is most dangerous
fellow human beings but the worst
mosquitoes literally billions of people
are at risk of Contracting Dengue fever
from mosquitoes and hundreds of
thousands die from mosquito-borne
malaria every year new threats like zika
continue to pose a global Public Health
threat such as the World Health
Organization suggested delaying
pregnancy in zika affected areas around
the world what's the best mosquito
repellent to wear there are products
like Permethrin a product originally
derived from chrysanthemums
interestingly that can be applied to
clothes but what about repellents you
actually put on your skin DEET is the
repellent to beat consider the gold
standard of protection when it's crucial
not to get bitten it was developed back
in the 1940s for use by the military
it's long been considered the first line
mosquito repellent Effectiveness wise 20
to 50 percent DEET repellents provide up
to several hours of protection that's
rubbed on the skin though DET
impregnated wrist bands don't work
repelling leaders only from areas
covered by the band which I guess you
could say about non-deep impregnated
wristbands detour citronella wristbands
have been clocked at working more
broadly for only 12 to 18 seconds
safety wise deed is considered safe even
in the second and third trimesters of
pregnancy and in children as long as
they're older than two months now it
should be noted that DEET can damage
Plastics and synthetic materials
therefore care should be taken when it's
used around plastic watches eyeglasses
and synthetic fabrics nylon is okay but
it's been found to damage spandex rayon
acetate and pigmented leather in
addition to plastic and vinyl
DEET is absorbed Through Your Skin into
your bloodstream but it's cleared from
your system within a few hours does it
have any adverse effects DEET is
probably far less toxic than many people
believe diet has a remarkable safety
profile after now more than a half
century of use and billions of
applications fewer than 50 cases of
serious toxic effects have been
documented in the medical literature
since 1960 and most of them were solved
most reported cases of adverse or lethal
events involved overuse or incorrect use
of the product incorrect use as in
chugging it to commit suicide
what's a correct usage read and follow
all directions on the product label only
applied to intact non-irritated skin do
not apply near eyes and mouth and only
sparingly around ears that's to avoid
accidental eye exposure or ingestion it
can be applied to the face but don't
spray it in your face spray it on your
hands and then you can dab on but still
avoid the eyes and mouth apply it to
children so they don't swallow any just
use enough to cover Exposed Skin or on
the outside of clothing Not underneath
and then once you're back inside wash it
off with soap and water and wash any
treated clothing if you do have a
reaction stop using it wash it off call
your local Poison Control Center and if
you go to your doctor bring the bottle
so which mosquito repellent works best
well in head-to-head tests deep crushed
it but this was in reference to a study
published about 20 years ago anything
new on the market that won't melt your
eyeglasses we'll find out next
[Music]
thank you